<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>mohdomama.github.io/amu2ias</title>
   
   <link></link>
   <description>Bringing the civil services legacy back to AMU</description>
   <language>en-uk</language>
   <managingEditor> </managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Noorul Hasan</title>
	  <link>/amu2ias//noorul-hasan</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-01-25T00:00:00+05:30</pubDate>
	  <guid>/amu2ias//noorul-hasan</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
  <p>AIR 625, CSE 2014 (IPS)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://amu2ias.files.wordpress.com/2017/12/img-20171222-wa0077-53842821.jpg" alt="Image" /></p>

<h4 id="basic-education">Basic Education</h4>
<p>I belong to a very small village named Harraypur,District – Pilibhit ( UP ).My basic education up to 8th class was completed in government School i.e. Primary and Secondary schools of my village in Hindi Medium. From 6th Class I started learning English Alphabet. Later on I did my 9th and 10th from Gurunanak Higher Secondary School ,Bhaisah Dist-Pilibhit.After completing my 10th we shifted in Bareilly as my father got Group  job in Bareilly .Here I took admission in Manohar Bhushan Inter College and completed my 10+2 .Though I was in Hindi medium but I remained topper in almost all the classes.</p>

<p>How I improved myself from a Hindi medium background to English</p>

<p>I completed my B.Tech from Aligarh Muslim University in the year 2009.This was the place where I developed myself and prepared my personality for civil service and corporate world.</p>

<p>Firstly, for improving English we formed a forum called Illumini (a peer group of 10 friends) where we used to discuss various national and international issue. In this forum we used to conduct mock interviews, GDs, debate etc.This forum has prepared my personality for CSE and other exams.</p>

<p>I was also the part of a college forum called @INGENIOUSSOLUTIONS right from first year. In this I worked for 4 years continuously and learned many things including how to speak English. This was the forum where seniors advised juniors to improve their personality and prepare them for future job opportunities. This was extremely useful for my personality development.</p>

<p>I was also part of University Literary Club but here I was not in any leadership role but learned many things from students who used to come to participate in Essay writing,Debates,Extempore,Quizzing etc.</p>

<p>Other than that I improved myself by participating in various literary activities as well as in sports activities of college and various residential Halls.</p>

<p>Thus I used AMU’s resources in the best possible manner to improve myself. So the ground work for civil service was already done in AMU .</p>

<h4 id="preparation-of-upsc">Preparation of UPSC</h4>
<p>After working 14 months in Siemens and 1 year in Department of Atomic Energy I realized I need to start preparation as I wanted to contribute to the society in a better manner as well as I was not satisfied with my professional advancement .So I started preparation in the year 2012. I did not join any coaching. I was full time working during my preparation phase. In 2013, I have given my first serious attempt (though first attempt was in 2012 where I could not clear prelims)and alhamdolilah I was able to crack Prelims ,and mains though in interview I could not score well (121 out of 275).Because of interview I could not make it in the final list. But I again started my preparation with full energy and in 2014 exam I was able to crack this it with rank 625 (Allocated IPS). Moreover this time I scored 190 marks in interview. I have taken English medium for all the stages of exam although I was from pure Hindi medium background. It was possible because I worked really hard to improve myself during my 4 years stay in AMU.</p>

<h4 id="message-to-youth-and-civil-service-aspirants-">Message to Youth and Civil Service Aspirants-</h4>

<p>Dream as big as possible but always prepare yourself for Plan B. Even after plan B, Plan C must be there. As in my case if I could not get success in civil I was having my alternate career in Department of Atomic Energy.
Decide your destination as early as possible and start working towards it.
In my opinion Success=Summation of each day work carried out for years
As in my case I worked a lot in my college to improve my personality and learning English. So you ll have to introspect your weakness and ll have to work upon them for years. So divide your target in the years, months, weeks and days and move ahead a little everyday. Achieve something every day.</p>

<p>For achieving your goal you need not be very intelligent .You need not be the best among your peers but you need to have passion to achieve your goal. As I was from very normal schools but I was having passion to achieve my target and I worked hard for that.
There is no discrimination with Muslim Youth/or with anyone in civil services .If you are having knowledge and expertise, you can crack any exam.
Try to get best possible guidance from your seniors .It is always better to learn from the experience of others rather than wasting your own time for years.
Never get demoralize from failures .Civil service exam is the test for patience and self confidence. So fail but fail better everytime. In.In the end you’ll get success.</p>

<h4 id="prelims-strategy-">Prelims strategy-</h4>

<p>It is one of the trickiest part of whole exam where one has to work really hard. Now only General Studies paper-1 counts in final ranking thus even one mark is very important. For general strategies my strategy was as follows–</p>

<ul>
  <li>Indian Polity-Laxmikanth (2-3 time reading)</li>
  <li>Modern History-Spectrum+NCERT(Bipin Chandra)</li>
  <li>Ancient history and culture-NCERT +CCRT website</li>
  <li>Geography-6-12th NCERT +Barnwal</li>
  <li>Economic-9-12 NCERT+Ramesh Singh book</li>
  <li>Environment-Ncert+IGNOU notes</li>
  <li>Science-9th and 10th ICSE books of biology .I did not study physics and chemistry</li>
  <li>Current Affairs-The Hindu+All India Radio+Rajya Sabha TV</li>
  <li>India Year Book+Economic Survey+Budget</li>
  <li>Practice of objective through whatapps group</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="mains-exam">Mains Exam</h4>

<h5 id="optional-strategypublic-administration-">Optional Strategy(Public Administration)-</h5>

<p>For public administration I started with Prasad and Prasad .After completing this book I purchased Mohanty ‘s Class notes from Mukherjee Nagar. After completing these two things I did advance study of selected topic from following books-</p>

<h5 id="paper-1-">Paper 1-</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Naidu’s book on public Administration (for understanding basic terminology of public admin)</li>
  <li>Mohit Bhattacharya(Bible of Public Ad)</li>
  <li>Fadia and Fadia (for very few topics)</li>
  <li>Public Administration-1 by Mr Aribam(KBC nano publication)</li>
  <li>IGNOU’s MPA notes(for few topics)</li>
  <li>IGNOU’s video (https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BRYJY0IzE1k&amp;list=PLj9gkP-MB8SH2RTvighfwyDl_1WgQmILw)</li>
  <li>CEC/UGC video (https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLNsppmbLKJ8IcEeognFbwtfcP0JGJ92n7)</li>
  <li>IIPA jounal(not in depth)</li>
  <li>A lot of discussion on Administrative thinkers with my friends Owais Jafri , Faraz , Arsalan.</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="paper-2">Paper 2</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Laxmikant for Indian Polity (already coverd in GS)</li>
  <li>Rajni Goyal and Arora</li>
  <li>Awasthi and Awasthi</li>
  <li>Public Administration-2 by Mr Aribam(KBC nano publication)</li>
  <li>2nd ARC report(only recommendation)</li>
  <li>IIPA journal(selected)</li>
  <li>The hindu and Rajya Sabha TV for current affairs</li>
  <li>Discussion with my friend on each and every topic</li>
  <li>Beside that I did lot of practice of previous 5 years papers. I also joined a test series .</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="gs-strategy">GS strategy</h4>

<p>GS is my one of the strongest area as I am reading newspaper right from 5th class(Hindi paper in those days). I used to listen news and TV debates. Thus I was already having opinion on various issues and during preparation phase I followed newspaper (Hindu),All India Radio,Rajya Sabha TV and Internet extensively.</p>

<h5 id="gs-paper-1">GS Paper 1</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Culture- CCRT and NCERT Ancient</li>
  <li>World Hitory-Old NCERT of Arjun Dev+some discussion with friends</li>
  <li>Modern History-Bipin Chandra +Ncert old one</li>
  <li>History after Independence-Bipin Chandra</li>
  <li>Societ-NCERT and newspaper+Ram Ahuja’s books for selected topics</li>
  <li>Geography-NCERT old(6,7,8,9,10,11,12)+Barnwal</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="gs-paper-2">GS Paper 2</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Indian Polity-Laxmikanth</li>
  <li>Other part was already covered in Public Administration</li>
  <li>Selected topic from Internet</li>
  <li>IR –from Newspaper+Vajiram class note</li>
  <li>Newpaper+Rajya Sabha+all India radio</li>
  <li>Discussion with friends</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="gs-paper-3">GS Paper 3</h5>
<ul>
  <li>Indian Economy-NCERT 9-12th +Ramesh Singh +Uma kapila for selected topic3.</li>
  <li>Newpaper+Rajya Sabha+all India radio</li>
  <li>Selected topic from Internet</li>
  <li>Science and Technology-Vision Ias compilation+newspaper</li>
  <li>Internal Security-IDSA book+newspaper</li>
  <li>Discussion with friends</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="gs-paper-4">GS Paper 4</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Subbarao books on ethics</li>
  <li>Insight India ‘s class notes</li>
  <li>Case studies from Menzel</li>
  <li>Case studies’ discussion with friends</li>
  <li>Essay–This is my weakest area .I only wrote 3-4 essays .So I advice aspirant to write at least 10 essays before appearing for mains and get it checked by experience teacher.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="interview">Interview</h4>
<p>The most important part of this exam is personality test. You can’t make personality overnight .So you have to work throughout your life to prepare for this. Thus one has to work on his personality while in school or college.As I have involved in number of activities during my college days in Aligarh Muslim University so I was at ease in this part.</p>

<p>I have completed each and every part of my biodata. Few areas are as follows</p>

<ul>
  <li>My village ,district I lived and State</li>
  <li>Schools I attended and college,university.</li>
  <li>My engineering Background.</li>
  <li>My Fathers’s profession.</li>
  <li>My work experience(Siemens and Nuclear energy)</li>
  <li>Muslim issues+some controversial issues</li>
  <li>Current affairs</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="interview-transcript">Interview Transcript</h4>

<p>Background – Electrical engineering
Working in Nuclear Power Corporation
Chairman – Prof H C Gupta</p>

<p>Chairman-</p>
<ul>
  <li>1.why was protest at kundankulam.</li>
  <li>
    <ol>
      <li>Why in  india ,there is  protest everywhere even if one wants to establish niddle making plant.</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>3.what can be done to stop protest.</li>
  <li>4.what is the level of electricity generation in india</li>
  <li>5.what is electricity deficit?</li>
  <li>
    <ol>
      <li>how many nuclear power plant are there in india?how many power station?</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>7.how much power generated  through nuclear energy what is the percentage of it ?</li>
  <li>8.which country generate largest electricity using nuclear fission</li>
  <li>9.why is in india state not purchasing electricity from power grid
Member1-</li>
  <li>1.Do u know about parliamentary privelege.Tell me what are those why are these incorporated in constitution.</li>
  <li>2.who ll take action n what action if a parliamentarian misbehave in parliament.</li>
  <li>3.can police act against member of parliament during session</li>
  <li>4.what is magna carta ?what was its relevance.</li>
  <li>5.what is fundamental right? difference with dpsp</li>
  <li>6.what is human right ,legal right ,n fundamental right</li>
  <li>7.can supreme court advice government? How? recent example of any such advice(2G case)
Member2.</li>
  <li>1.how much electricity ll b needed if in india all the villages and industry be given 24*7</li>
  <li>2.swings bowling principle</li>
  <li>3.some background question</li>
</ul>

<p>Member 3</p>
<ul>
  <li>1.what is group discussion what quality it checks…</li>
  <li>2.Turbine n principle of generation of electricity</li>
  <li>3.what are parts of generators?how 3phase power is generated…</li>
  <li>4.some more on group discussion n electrical engineering</li>
  <li>Member 4</li>
  <li>1.what is difference between shia n sunni</li>
  <li>2.what is the percentage of each sect in the world n in india?</li>
  <li>3.Iran n Iraq ‘s shia sunni population?</li>
  <li>4.turbo generators n jets?</li>
</ul>

<p>Chairman-again</p>

<ul>
  <li>1.Who was noorul hasan n his contribution n his political career</li>
  <li>2.Who was gurunak n 9 gurus of sikh(school name)</li>
  <li>3.Are u shia or sunni</li>
</ul>

<p>Chairman said regarding completion of interview…i thanked him n other members ..interview duration 40 min</p>

<h4 id="my-scorecard">My scorecard</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Essay 106</li>
  <li>GS1 -87</li>
  <li>GS2-93</li>
  <li>GS3-90</li>
  <li>GS4-109</li>
  <li>Pub Ad-219</li>
  <li>Interview -190</li>
</ul>

<p>All the best !!!!!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Mohammad Sana Akhtar</title>
	  <link>/amu2ias//mohammad-sana-akhtar</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-01-25T00:00:00+05:30</pubDate>
	  <guid>/amu2ias//mohammad-sana-akhtar</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
  <p>AIR 211, CSE 2014 (IPS)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://amu2ias.files.wordpress.com/2015/09/msa.jpg?w=300&amp;h=200" alt="Image" /></p>

<h4 id="background">Background</h4>

<p>I joined AMU for pursuing Computer Science Engineering.</p>

<p>After passing my Engineering in 2010, I joined STMicroelectronics and have been working there since then.</p>

<h4 id="preparation-of-cse">Preparation of CSE</h4>

<p>I have given three attempts. The 2012 attempt was more like testing the waters without much preparation. 2013 attempt was serious but I couldn’t clear the prelims. In 2014, I cleared the exam with 211 Rank.</p>

<p>I was motivated towards CSE as it provides ample opportunities to impact the life of so many people in a meaningful way which is difficult in most other jobs.</p>

<h4 id="message-to-youth-and-civil-service-aspirants">Message to Youth and Civil Service Aspirants</h4>

<p>I believe that first a person should analyze one’s skills one is good at and try to go for those fields which require those particular skills.</p>

<h4 id="prelims-strategy">Prelims strategy</h4>

<p>In the ever changing scenario of CSE, One thing is sure that General Studies will always play a major role in the CSE. In 2014, the Paper 2 (Aptitude paper) has been made qualifying which means that only Paper 1 (General Studies paper) will be counted for rankings. However, people should always try to improve their comprehension skills in English as writing skills are important for mains point of view and there maybe changes which can bring the Paper 2 back for rank calculations.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Indian Polity- Laxmikanth</li>
  <li>Modern History- NCERT(Bipin Chandra) + India’s Struggle for Freedom (Bipin Chandra)</li>
  <li>Ancient history and culture – I skipped most of the culture but I think NCERT + NIOS are good enough. Culture videos of unacademy on Youtube by Roman Saini are a good source for classical dances.</li>
  <li>Geography-G C Leong + Major topics from Physical geography notes of any coaching institute + Map practice of Rivers, Mountains, Sanctuaries</li>
  <li>Economy – Mrunal videos, PPTs and Economic Survey overview w.r.t. facts</li>
  <li>Environment – Shankar IAS Environment book + Independent Googling</li>
  <li>Science and Technology – From newspapers + BBC World Tech news</li>
  <li>Current Affairs -The Indian Express/The Hindu + Chronicle Magazine + Independent Googling + BBC World News</li>
  <li>After covering these resources, one maybe able to do only 30-40% of questions in pre with 100% surety which may not be sufficient to clear the exam. For a higher score, one has to take risks, especially when one is confused between just two choices. This is the change in my strategy for prelims between 2013 and 2014 attempts and it Clicked !!!.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="mains-exam">Mains Exam</h4>

<p>Optional Strategy (Geography)</p>

<p>For Geography, I relied on standard text books mentioned below alongwith coaching notes of Vajiram and Nitu Singh.</p>

<h5 id="paper-1-106-marks">Paper 1 (106 marks)</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Savindra Singh for Physical Geography + Nitu Singh notes</li>
  <li>Majid Hussain For Human Geography + Vajiram notes</li>
  <li>Shankar IAS Environment book for Environment + Newspapers</li>
  <li>Settlement Geography from Majid Hussain + Vajiram notes</li>
  <li>Perspective in Human Geography from Vajiram notes</li>
  <li>Models, laws etc from Vajiram notes
    <h5 id="paper-2-146-marks">Paper 2 (146 marks)</h5>
  </li>
  <li>Physical India from Khullar and Nitu Singh notes</li>
  <li>Maps from Nitu Singh maps compendium + independent Googling of the recent locations</li>
  <li>Current Issues from Mrunal, The Indian Express/The Hindu
    <h5 id="test-series">Test Series</h5>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>I didn’t attend any test series. In my view, those who feel that they are not comfortable with expressing their views easily, they can join test series for mains. Else mere practicing the tests available in market is also good enough.</p>

<h4 id="gs-strategy">GS strategy</h4>

<p>Long term reading these days is the single most important way of achieving good results in GS papers. One should read widely from various sources like newspapers (The hindu, The Indian Express), magazines (Chronicle) and non-fiction books covering different aspects of social issues.</p>

<h5 id="gs-paper-1-96-marks">GS Paper 1 (96 marks)</h5>

<ul>
  <li>Culture – I skipped most of the culture here too but I think NCERT + NIOS are good enough. Culture videos of unacademy on facebook by Roman Saini are a good source for classical dances.</li>
  <li>World Hitory – ALS printed notes + coverage in newspapers about past happenings like anniversaries of important events etc</li>
  <li>Modern History-Bipin Chandra</li>
  <li>History after Independence – India After Gandhi by Ramachandra Guha</li>
  <li>Society – Newspapers</li>
  <li>Geography – My optional but I recommend basics of physical geography from any coaching institute notes like Vajiram/Nitu Singh
    <h5 id="gs-paper-2-100-marks">GS Paper 2 (100 marks)</h5>
  </li>
  <li>Indian Polity-Laxmikanth</li>
  <li>IR – From Newspapers + Mrunal</li>
  <li>Independent Googling</li>
  <li>Newspapers
    <h5 id="gs-paper-3-76-marks">GS Paper 3 (76 marks)</h5>
  </li>
  <li>Internal Security – ALS coaching notes</li>
  <li>Economy – Economic Survey is a must read + mrunal</li>
  <li>Science and technology – Newspapers, BBC World Technology News
    <h5 id="gs-paper-4-93-marks">GS Paper 4 (93 marks)</h5>
  </li>
  <li>Justice Course of Harvard from edx.org taught by Professor Sandler</li>
  <li>Meaning of basic terms from Chronicle Magazine</li>
  <li>Most importantly, one should be ethical himself to score well here. Familiarity with Indian constitution, Fundamental Rights/Duties, awareness about important social issues plaguing the country are required.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="essay-148-marks">Essay (148 marks)</h4>

<p>Got my highest marks among written papers in Essay. Frankly speaking, I never practiced writing a single essay. Again, those who have difficulty in expressing their views should practice. To right a good essay, my strategy was to write on a topic which is scientific/objective in nature and then cover as many dimensions of the topic as possible. Also, try to relate the topic with current happenings of the country and the world. During the exam, I used mind map technique to generate as many ideas about the topic as possible.</p>

<p>This time, there were two essays asked. I wrote on “Increasing competition faced by youth” and “Tourism ”.</p>

<h4 id="interview-168-marks">Interview (168 marks)</h4>

<p>Interview in my view is usually a reflection of oneself. To perform well, one should know about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Oneself – Place to where one belongs, Family Background, school, college, job, current place of stay etc</li>
  <li>Subject studied in College</li>
  <li>Subject taken as optional</li>
  <li>One’s own job if working or ever worked</li>
  <li>Current Affairs specially in the fields of economy, international relations, current social happenings, recent laws etc</li>
  <li>Hobbies – Mine was playing football</li>
</ul>

<h5 id="interview-transcript">Interview Transcript</h5>

<p>Chairman – Mr Vinay Mittal</p>

<ul>
  <li>You have sports background?</li>
  <li>When do you play in office</li>
  <li>Indian sports is changing? How?</li>
  <li>What’s the new way of these leagues?</li>
  <li>How many games have seen this new system?</li>
  <li>Is the new system good?</li>
  <li>Why are these getting popular?</li>
  <li>How do these franchises earn money to fund the auction of the players?</li>
  <li>You work in a semiconductor company. What is a semiconductor?</li>
  <li>Why they are called semiconductor?</li>
  <li>What does your company specializes in?</li>
  <li>You work in an MNC, How would you prevent sexual harassment in your company?</li>
  <li>Is there some govt guideline regarding these in corporate sector?</li>
  <li>What are they?</li>
  <li>What else you would do?</li>
  <li>A geography question … Tourism based on geography…what is it called?</li>
  <li>What are India’s current problems in financial area?</li>
  <li>What is fiscal deficit?</li>
  <li>When is it good?</li>
  <li>What was India’s deficit this year?</li>
  <li>When do we say that fiscal situation is bad…3% or 5%…how?</li>
  <li>Who decides that it’s bad?</li>
  <li>What is shale oil?</li>
  <li>How is it diff from other sources?</li>
  <li>What are the 3 parts of democracy?</li>
  <li>Are CAG etc part of executive?</li>
  <li>But they also put check on executive…so are they not like judiciary?</li>
  <li>How does computer science helps in study of geography?</li>
  <li>He said, no not personally? For the geographic study?</li>
  <li>What is GPS ?</li>
  <li>What is it’s purpose?</li>
  <li>Does GPS helps in calls when you come from one place to another?</li>
  <li>What about CDMA?</li>
  <li>What is Greenwich?</li>
  <li>Why is it used?</li>
  <li>How is standard time calculated?</li>
  <li>So, how much is 1 degree?</li>
</ul>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Farha Hussain</title>
	  <link>/amu2ias//farha-hussain</link>
	  <author></author>
	  <pubDate>2018-01-25T00:00:00+05:30</pubDate>
	  <guid>/amu2ias//farha-hussain</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <blockquote>
  <p>AIR 267, CSE 2015, IRS</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="https://amu2ias.files.wordpress.com/2016/09/14138634_297158847316389_3808408826733944932_o.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300" alt="Image" /></p>

<p>Dear All,</p>

<p>I am FARHA HUSSAIN. I belong to Jhunjhunu district of Rajasthan and I cleared UPSC Civil Services Examination this year with a rank of 267. I want to share my story with you all and try and contribute towards motivating young students and aspirants. I cannot make any tall claims like a lot of successful aspirants of having suffered hardships or any lack of facilities. I have led a fairly comfortable life and have extremely understanding parents. There are dozens of civil servants in my family, thus the atmosphere to excel and do something in the public life was always there without anyone reinforcing it or talking about it at all. These things work as a great motivation, however, it also brings in a lot of expectations from you and then starts the struggle to try and match upto them. When you have everyone’s eyes set on you to see where you end up, it really weighs you down. Also, for girls there is a lot that the society expects from her.. to get married early, to settle as a happy housewife. If a woman thinks about herself first, she is thought to be selfish. I feel we must always be respectful to others’ wishes and thoughts but please do not let it stop you from achieving something that is dear to you. Listen to everyone, but follow your heart!</p>

<p>Despite coming from such a family, I too have faced a lot of these things and at times it took a toll on me. But in times of distress, I never stopped believing in my capabilities and I was certain I would make a mark surely. And my efforts paid when I became the second muslim girl from Rajasthan to clear the UPSC Civil Service Examination. This exam is definitely a test of intelligence, but it also tests your mental strength, patience and the like. It does not require you to be a master in each field of study, you are only expected to do a generalized study which I feel translates to studying SMART, rather than studying like a maniac cutting yourself from the world. I think studying 5-6 hours a day is enough provided you are consistent throughout the year. It tests your knowledge about the things happening in the world, around you etc.</p>

<p>I recommend the following combined strategy for Prelims and Mains as I never studied separately for them:</p>
<h4 id="books-for-general-studies">BOOKS for GENERAL STUDIES:</h4>
<ul>
  <li>NCERTS – class 6 to 12th if you have times. Otherwise do atlas class 11 and 12th NCERTs.</li>
  <li>Polity by Lakshmikanth</li>
  <li>Environment by ShankarIAS</li>
  <li>Geography – NCERTs, GC Leong, Wizard Publication</li>
  <li>Culture – Nitin Singhania</li>
  <li>CSAT Guide by Arihant</li>
  <li>History – Tamil Nadu Board Textbook for class 11,12 and Rajiv Ahir’s Modern History; Modern history by Bipin Chandra</li>
  <li>India After Independence by Bipin Chandra</li>
  <li>Economy by Ramesh Singh</li>
  <li>Economic Survey</li>
  <li>India Year Book</li>
  <li>Yojana Magazine</li>
  <li>Newspaper : Indian Express</li>
  <li>Current Affair Notes by Vision IAS Institute</li>
  <li>Reports of Finance Commission, Centre State relations etc.</li>
  <li>Latest Bills, Acts from presidia website</li>
  <li>Websites : Mrunal.org, insightsonindia.com, iasbaba.com</li>
  <li>For LAW Optional:</li>
  <li>Torts – Bangia</li>
  <li>IPC – R&amp;D</li>
  <li>Constitution – V N shukla</li>
  <li>International Law – S K Kapoor</li>
  <li>Contract – Jhabvala
For other topics I downloaded Bare Acts from internet and made notes from various articles on the internet. For recent case laws please buy Delhi University compendiums.
Articles from legalserviceindia.com, lawandotherthings blog website</li>
</ul>

<p>Follow latest cases from newspapers, internet and Quote them in your answers! Always write in points, quote section numbers if possible, write case laws. If you don’t remember the name of the case, write the facts at least! I remember reading a blog by one of the toppers and he had said when he could not recall any case laws he wrote about a Madhuri Dixit movie and how there was a controversy regarding copyright infringement relating to it.
When you can’t recall any case laws, say in a question about defamation, you can at least explain defamation by quoting the recent news about Kejriwal and cases filed against him regarding an issue. It would give the impression that you are well aware of the things around you and understand them well.
I strongly feel that most questions are current affairs based, so they are the most important portion of the syllabus. Do not ignore Newspaper reading at any cost. I helps you even in improving English Language which is a must. For ANSWER WRITING, please try and write in points, draw many diagrams, mind maps, quote from reports, data and recent schemes of government. Always write recent happenings in each paper, even in optional.
Never write extremely negative answers. Please write answers like a government servant, as if you are already an IAS officer. Do not criticise the government at every step. Always conclude your answer with a suggestion to improve things and on a positive note. Also, write one answer everyday. It will help you immensely.
Please remember, When you decide to take another step when you don’t think you can, that is what makes all the difference in your life! Go ahead, dream big, aspire high… Good luck to you.. Hope to meet you soon as an esteemed colleague very soon!</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
